hello everybody I'm today in this video
I want to talk or not talk I'm gonna
just give you my advice in the path that
you should follow when you're learning
to program and when you are learning to
become a front-end or a full-stack
developer
[Music]
if you are new to everything and you
want to make websites you wanna make you
wanna make your idea come true and you
want to be a freelancer or whatever the
first thing that you should start
programming learning sorry
it's a HTML and CSS that is like the
cornerstone of all the front-end and web
development that you want to do HTML CSS
is like the first thing that everybody
must learn because that teaches you a
little bit of text editors a little bit
of how the browser's work a little bit
or how the files work it is not
programming but still is a very good
start
right
[Music]
so after you touch html/css
then the next step is to learn a bit of
JavaScript and by a bit I don't mean by
a book of JavaScript or like get some
crazy course in JavaScript no just do
very small stuff on JavaScript stuff
that you can understand and don't learn
stuff that you don't need so when you
say learn JavaScript there is people
that learn JavaScript for the whole life
even mean I still don't know how to do
something I still discover something new
so it's really big to say you learn
JavaScript right well you should learn
what you should focus is learn vanilla
JavaScript vanilla JavaScript is the
term that we use for JavaScript without
any libraries javascript without any
makeup just ugly raw JavaScript all
right learn it on the way that you feel
constable modifying HTML with JavaScript
this means making HTML interactive we'd
only directly we know help from a
library
this is my second point
you shouldn't learn libraries at the
beginning because what you learn is the
library but you don't understand how it
works
under it and what's happening behind the
curtain right so if you start learning
jQuery for example you're going to
understand how jQuery works you're going
to understand how to make a fading in
jQuery or something like that we're not
going to understand how does the fading
happen or what is this function doing
you don't know what the is a
function all you know is jQuery stuff
right so try to stay away from libraries
try to stay away from any kind of
framework and all that stuff
learn vanilla JavaScript first right and
I have three projects for you that will
show you that you know JavaScript pretty
well the phrasing will be make a
to-do list that is like the hello world
of JavaScript or I make a to-do list
that way the first thing okay that to-do
list and you good now bit next thing
that you could do is try to learn how to
make small as more interactions on your
website this means add some animations
when somebody clicks this means when
somebody Scrolls maybe show the header
of the website in a different way maybe
make a video player maybe somebody
stuff we can do maybe make a yeah just
interactions interactions interactions
on your website very small stuff all
right don't don't try to make a
nano Facebook which makes something
small just I click this button and you
show me a small pop-up small
notifications place a small chat window
some stuff like that that would be very
very small and it will be very very
simple for you to learn and also that
you will actually see on the screen
while you're learning all right never
never study something that you're not
going to use that is my advice to you
I always do a small stuff when you do
small stuff and you feel comfortable
without script then you can move on to
becoming a little bit more comfortable
but now with more complication a script
and you can open the door through small
libraries such as you can test a little
bit of jQuery you can test a little bit
of react and you can understand why
people use them and maybe when you are
doing for example the to-do list on
vanilla JavaScript but you realize like
hey this is no some part is complicated
this parts is repetitive maybe this is a
pain point and maybe later when you go
to react you're going to see how react
solves that pain point and this is going
to make you understand why people like
react because you suffered what
everybody suffered with vanilla
JavaScript and now you understand what
we act can do for you and this is when
it's good you don't do react because I
tell you to or because it's trendy is
because you actually understand the pain
points of making a JavaScript
application without a framework for
example
so now that you understand frameworks
it's time for you to do a little bit of
back end because you even if you don't
want to do it forever you need to
understand how backing works right so
now that you've been learning JavaScript
and now that you know a little bit of
libraries and you're comfortable with
the console and everything starting to
look into nowadays look into Express and
look into how to make a small server to
show your website this is all very
simple stuff all right but it's gonna
give you a very good view and what you
can do with JavaScript and what you can
do with the front end and with the back
end and after you do all this so for
this HTML CSS then vanilla JavaScript
then one library then back end with
node.js and Express for example there's
a lot of tutorials and it's a very solid
project after you're done with all these
things then ask yourself do I like
JavaScript
do I like react do I like node.js
if the answer is no at least you already
have this framework of how to learn
something and you understand what is
required on the back end what is
required on the front end and then you
can say you know what I don't like
node.js I hate your script I'm gonna
learn Python but now at least you
understand how you can make a website on
the front end and you can put back a
Python on the back end all right
don't learn Python just we could learn
Python out of a necessity don't learn
react
just because learn react out of a pain
point that you have before and now
you're solving all right so when
JavaScript becomes a pain in the ass for
you then you learn Python for example
when vanilla JavaScript becomes a
praying they ask for you then you learn
react this is the approach that I will
suggest you to do don't in my opinion
don't waste a time focusing too much on
databases focusing too much in Linux
focusing too much in consoles focusing
too much on speed and all that stuff
don't waste time on this this can come
later but first just get up quick
landscape what you can do and do stuff
so that would be my roadmap for
JavaScript and for front-end and
back-end development if you wanna become
a full spec go ahead I think is more fun
but that'll be my advice let me know if
you agree or if you don't agree and let
me know what you think on the comments
thank you for watching and bye bye
[Music]